{
  "reference_number": "9539",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "It is crucial to set certain aspects of the legislation in stone NOW. Let's take this opportunity to fix a deadline for zero emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I don't believe we can buy our way to zero carbon, it has to be a commitment as a country - we need to do it ourselves."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, we could bring the date forward if progress is good. We should also be realistic enough to push the date back, but only in\n exceptional circumstances - it is crucial that no future government can wriggle out of the deal."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "The budget and targets should be independent of the government"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We need to work with iwi and the business sector to try to ensure that we have everyone's support, but at the end of the day, the\nfuture of our planet can not be compromised. The important thing will be for governments to be committed and transparent."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "Independence is key"
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There will be opposition to the bill, and there will be companies who will struggle to meet the demands of the bill. Offering support\nand networking to those companies and organisations should be part of the process"
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This Bill is an opportunity for New Zealand to take a stand internationally and demonstrate its commitment to stalling climate change.\n\nA strong and committed stance will gain NZ international respect, and will also benefit the tourist industry, which, let's face it, may go\na long way to offsetting any resultant losses in the mining and agricultural sectors. The success of the Bill hinges on the\n\nindependence of the Climate Commission, and the fact that the effects are long-term, and legally binding to successive\ngovernments. I believe that we should not underplay the influence and assistance we can provide for local (South Pacific) neighbours\n\nwith regard to climate change, and urge the legislators to view the Bill on a Pacific, not simply national, level. I believe there should be\nflexibility in the role of the Commission to be expanded in the future to include, for example, assisting our neighbours to implement\nsimilar measures, ocean clean-ups, reduction of solid waste, etc in the future. Wouldn't it be fantastic if the climate commissions of\n\ncountries such as NZ and the UK had international influence and could put pressure on less conscientious nations to follow our lead.\nPlease don't let us miss this opportunity to do the right thing, New Zealand. There will be economic effects, but the health of our\n\npeople and our planet has to come before profit."
    }
  ]
}
